(Wildlife squawking)
(Man panting)
(Natives yelling)
(Yelling continues)
({screams) {Screeches)
Damn it, man! That was our
ride! You just stunned our ride!
On, great.
(Native yells)
Run!
(Natives ululating)
(Speaking local language)
What the hell did you take?
I have no idea,
but they were bowing to it.
Kirk to shuttle one.
Locals are out of the kill zone.
You are clear. Repeat.
Spock, get in there, neutralize the
volcano and let's get out of here.
(Rumbling)
We have to do this now!
I told the captain
the shuttle wasn't built
for this kind of heat.
Captain, did the indigenous
life forms see you?
No, Mr. Spock, they did not.
The prime directive clearly states
there can be no interference
with the internal development
of alien civilizations.
I know what it says!
Which is why I'm running
through the jungle wearing a disguise!
Now drop off your super ice cube
and let's go! Kirk out!
You're good.
Sulu: If we're gonna do this,
we've got to do it now!
This ash is killing our coils.
You sure you don't want me
to go instead?
That would be highly illogical
as I am already outfitted...
Spock, I was kidding.
- You got this.
- Guys! We have to go! Now!
- (Both panting)
- (Natives yelling)
They're trying to kill us!
They're trying to kill us, Jim!
I'll see you in 90 seconds.
Do it, do it!
(Breathing heavily)
Automated male voice:
Prerequisite change, 2-7-3...
I can't hold this position.
Spock, I've got to pull you back up.
Negative. This is our only
chance to save this species.
If this volcano erupts, the planet dies.
Pull him back up. Now!
(Grunts)
Uhura: Spock, are you okay?
I am,
surprisingly, alive. Stand by.
We have to get him back.
I'll suit up. I'm gonna go down.
We have to abandon the shuttle.
- We can't just leave him, sulu!
- We don't have a choice!
Uhura, I'm sorry.
Spock, we're going back
to the enterprise.
We'll get you out of there.
Captain, I'm ditching the shuttle.
You've got to make it
to the enterprise on your own.
Kirk: Wonderful!
- Uhura! You ready to swim?
- I'm ready.
(Natives clamoring)
Jim!
Jim! The beach is that way!
Kirk: I know!
We're not going to the beach!
Bones: Oh, no, no, no!
(Natives speaking
with reverence)
I hate this!
I know you do!
(Both panting)
(Both scream)
Do you have any idea
how ridiculous it is
to hide a starship
on the bottom of the ocean?
We've been down here since last night!
The salt water's gonna ruin the...
Scotty! Where's Spock?
Still in the volcano, sir.
(Sighs)
(Breathing heavily)
(Groaning)
(Natives exclaiming in surprise)
(Screaming)
Chekov: Captain on the bridge!
Lieutenant, do we have
an open channel to Mr. Spock?
The heat's frying his comms,
but we still have contact.
Spock?
I have activated the device, captain.
When the countdown is complete,
the reaction should
render the volcano inert.
Bones: Yeah, and that's
gonna render him inert!
Do we have use of the transporters?
- Negative, sir.
- Not with these magnetic fields.
Kirk: I need to beam Spock
back to the ship.
Give me one way to do it.
Maybe if we had a direct line of sight.
- If we got closer...
- Scotty: Hold on, wee man!
You're talking about an active volcano!
Sir, if that thing erupts,
I cannae guarantee
we can withstand the heat!
I don't know that we can
maintain that kind of altitude.
Our shuttle was concealed
by the ash cloud,
but the enterprise is too large.
If utilized in a rescue effort,
it would be revealed
to the indigenous species.
Spock, nobody knows
the rules better than you,
but there has got to be an exception.
None. Such action violates
the prime directive.
Shut up, Spock! We're trying
to save you, damn it!
Doctor, the needs of
the many outweigh the needs of the few.
Spock, we're talking about your life!
- Spock: The rule cannot be broken...
- (Line disconnects)
Kirk: Spock!
Try to get him back online.
Chekov: Ninety seconds
to detonations.
If Spock were here and I were there,
what would he do?
He'd let you die.
(Breathing heavily)
(All chanting)
(Explosion)
(All clamoring)
(Natives exclaiming in shock)
(Shouting)
(Gasping in awe)
(All clamoring)
(Breathing heavily)
(Beeping)
(Door opening)
Spock!
You all right?
Captain, you let them see our ship.
(Sighs) He's fine.
- Uhura: Bridge to captain kirk.
- Yes, lieutenant.
Is commander Spock on board, sir?
- Kirk: Safely and soundly.
- (Relieved sigh)
Please notify him that his device
has successfully detonated.
Kirk: You hear that?
Congratulations, Spock.
You just saved the world.
You violated the prime directive.
Oh, come on, Spock.
They saw us. Big deal.
(All chattering excitedly)
(Beeping)
(Conversing indistinctly)
(Door opens)
(Woman sniffles)
(Sobbing)
Man: I can save her.
What did you say?
Your daughter.
I can save her.
Who are you?
(Lively '90$ hip-hop
music playing)
(Communicator beeping)
(Panting)
- Oh, Jim. Come on, let it go.
- (Muttering)
Jim!
You're not actually gonna
answer that, are you?
Kirk: Spock, I'm telling you,
this is why he called. I can feel it.
Your feeling aside,
I consider it highly unlikely
that we will be selected
for the new program.
Why else would pike want to see us?
Forget about seniority.
They gave us the newest ship
in the fleet.
I mean, who else
are they gonna send out?
Spock: I can think of
numerous possibilities.
A five-year mission, Spock!
That's deep space!
That's uncharted territory!
Think how incredible that's gonna be.
Hey, ladies. Jim kirk.
- "Uneventful."
- kirk: Admiral?
It's the way you described the survey of
nibiru in your captain's log.
Yes, sir, I didn't want to waste your time
going over the details.
Tell me more about this volcano.
Data says it was highly volatile.
If it were to erupt,
it would wipe out the planet.
Let's hope it doesn't, sir.
Something tells me it won't.
Well, sir, volatile is all relative.
Maybe our data was off.
Or maybe it didn't erupt
because Mr. Spock detonated
a cold fusion device
inside it right after a civilization
that's barely invented the wheel
happened to see a starship
rising out of their ocean!
That is pretty much how
you describe it, is it not?
- Admiral...
- You filed a report?
Why didn't you tell me?
I incorrectly assumed that you would be
truthful in your captain's log.
Yeah, I would have been
if I didn't have to save your life.
A fact for which I am
immeasurably grateful
and the very reason I felt it necessary
to take responsibility for the actions...
(Scoffs)
Take responsibility, yeah.
That'd be so noble, pointy,
if you weren't also
throwing me under the bus.
"Pointy"? Is that
a derogatory reference to...
Gentlemen.
Starfleet's mandate is to explore and
observe, not to interfere.
Had the mission gone
according to plan, admiral,
the indigenous species would never
have been aware of our interference.
That's a technicality.
I am vulcan, sir.
We embrace technicality.
Are you giving me attitude, Spock?
I'm expressing
multiple attitudes simultaneously, sir.
To which are you referring?
Out.
You're dismissed, commander.
(Door opens)
You have any idea what
a pain in the ass you are?
I think so, sir.
So tell me what you did wrong.
What's the lesson to be learned here?
Never trust a vulcan.
Now, see, you can't
even answer the question. You lied.
On an official report, you lied.
You think the rules don't apply to you
'cause you disagree with them.
That's why you talked me
into signing up in the first place.
It's why you gave me your ship.
I gave you my ship because
I saw a greatness in you.
And now, I see you haven't
got an ounce of humility.
What was I supposed to do,
let Spock die?
You're missing the point.
I don't think I am, sir.
What would you have done?
I wouldn't have risked
my first officer's life
in the first place!
You were supposed to survey a planet,
not alter its destiny!
You violated a dozen
starfleet regulations
and almost got everyone
under your command killed.
Except I didn't!
You know how many
crew members I've lost? Not one!
That's your problem,
you think you're infallible!
You think you can't make a mistake.
It's a pattern with you!
- The rules are for other people!
- Some should be.
And what's worse is you using blind luck
to justify your playing god!
Given the circumstances,
this has been brought to
admiral Marcus's attention.
He convened a special tribunal,
to which I was not invited.
You understand what starfleet
regulations mandate
be done at this point.
They've taken the enterprise
away from you.
They're sending you
back to the academy.
Admiral, listen...
- No, I'm not going to listen.
- I can justify...
Why should I listen?
I'm not going to listen.
You don't listen to anybody but yourself!
I understand regulation,
but every decision I've made...
No! I can't listen!
You don't comply with the rules,
you don't take responsibility
for anything,
and you don't respect the chair.
You know why?
Because you're not ready for it.
(Breathing heavily)
(Beeping)
(Indistinct conversations)
(Machine humming)
(Door opens)
Man: (On pa)
Attention, personnel.
Blue security clearance now
permitted for airlock access.
Woman: I'm going to need
three titanium...
Automated male voice: Radiation
protection is required in this area.
(Chattering continues
indistinctly)
(Computer beeps)
(Whining)
(People screaming)
(Mellow blues music playing)
(Clears throat)
(Exhales)
(Sighs)
How did you find me?
I know you better than you think I do.
The first time I found you
was in a dive like this.
Remember that? You got
your ass handed to you.
No, I didn't.
- You don't?
- No, that's not what happened.
- That was an epic beating.
- No, it wasn't.
You had napkins
hanging out of your nose.
- (Chuckles)
- Did you not?
Yeah, that was a good fight.
"A good fight."
I think that's your problem right there.
They gave her back to me.
The enterprise.
Congratulations.
Watch your back with
that first officer, though.
Spock's not going
to be working with me.
He's been transferred.
U. S. S. Bradbury.
You're going to be my first officer.
Yeah, Marcus took some convincing.
But every now and then
I can make a good case.
What did you tell him?
The truth.
That I believe in you.
That if anybody
deserves a second chance, it's Jim kirk.
(Sighs)
I don't know what to say.
That is a first.
It's going to be okay, son.
(Communicator beeps)
(Chirps)
"Emergency session, daystrom."
That's us.
Yeah.
Suit up.
Woman: (On pa) All starfleet
personnel, please be advised,
- new security protocols are in effect.
- Spock: Captain.
Not anymore, Spock. First officer.
I was demoted
and you were reassigned.
It is fortunate that the consequences
were not more severe.
(Sighs) You've got to be kidding me.
Captain, it was never my intention...
Not captain.
I saved your life, Spock.
You wrote a report, I lost my ship.
Commander, I see now
I should have alerted you
to the fact that I submitted the report.
Kirk: No, I'm familiar
with your compulsion
to follow the rules.
But you see, I can't do that.
Where I come from,
if someone saves your life,
you don't stab him in the back.
Vulcans cannot lie.
Then I'm talking
to the half-human part of you.
All right?
Do you understand
why I went back for you?
Commander Spock?
Frank Abbot, u. S. S. Bradbury.
Guess you're with me.
Yes, captain.
The truth is
I'm going to miss you.
(Sighs in frustration)
Abbot: Admiral Marcus, sir.
Thank you for convening
on such short notice.
Be seated.
By now, some of you
have heard what happened in London.
The target was a starfleet data archive.
Now it's a damned hole in the ground,
42 men and women are dead.
One hour ago,
I received a message
from a starfleet officer,
who confessed to
carrying out this attack,
that he was being
forced to do it by this man,
commander John Harrison.
He's one of our own.
And he is the man responsible
for this act of savagery.
For reasons unknown,
John Harrison has just declared
a one-man war against starfleet.
And under no circumstances
are we to allow this man
to escape federation space.
You here tonight represent
the senior command
of all the vessels in the region.
And in the name of those we lost,
you will run this bastard down.
This is a manhunt,
pure and simple, so let's get to work.
Earth's perimeter sensors
have not detected
any warp signatures leaving the system,
so we know he can't be far.
You will park your ships
in a blockade formation
then deploy search vehicles
and landing parties
to run down every lead.
This man has shown willingness
to kill innocent people,
so the rules of engagement are simple.
If you come across this man
and fear for your life
or the lives of those nearby,
you are authorized to
use deadly force on sight.
- What's in the bag?
- James, not now.
It doesn't seem odd to you
that he'd target an archive?
It's like bombing a library.
Chris? Everything okay there?
Yes, sir. Mr. Kirk is just acclimating
to his new position as first officer.
You got something to say, kirk, say it.
Tomorrow's too late.
I'm fine, sir. My apologies.
Spit it out, son. Don't be shy.
Why the archive?
All that information is public record.
If he really wanted to damage starfleet,
this could just be the beginning.
The beginning of what, Mr. Kirk?
Sir, in the event
of an attack, protocol mandates
that senior command gather
captains and first officers
at starfleet h.Q., right here
- in this room.
- Spock: It is curious Harrison
would commandeer a jumpship
without warp capabilities...
(Rumbling)
Clear the room!
(All screaming)
(Grunting)
(Turrets firing)
Woman: No!
(Screams)
We need an air defense team!
Daystrom conference room!
(Clamoring continues)
- Guard 1: Let's go!
- Guard 2: Cover me!
(Both groaning)
(Panting)
Guard 1: Target acquired.
Guard 2: Take him out!
Guard 1: Watch my flank!
Guard 3: Go, go, go!
Guard 4: Cover me!
(Breathing heavily)
(Grunts)
(Groaning)
(Pike groaning)
(Grunts)
Guard 1: Fire!
(Pike wheezing)
(Gasping)
(Grunts)
- (Grinding)
- (Engine sputtering)
(Pike breathing heavily)
(Sobbing)
(Sirens wailing)
(Thunder crashing)
(Communicator beeping)
(Communicator chirps)
Yeah?
Spock: Commander,
Mr. Scott has found something
in the wreckage of Harrison's ship.
He has asked to see us right away.
Scotty: Captain!
I found this in the crashed jumpship, sir.
- This is how the bastard got away.
- Kirk: What do you mean?
Scotty: It's a portable
transwarp beaming device.
Kirk: Well, can you figure out
where he went?
I already did, sir.
And you're no gonna like it.
(Device beeps)
He's gone to the one place we...
We just can't go.
Admiral, sir, he's not on earth.
(Panting) He's on kronos, sir.
I request my command be reinstated
and your permission to go after him.
Give us a minute.
- Kronos.
- Yes, sir.
So Harrison's gone
to the klingon homeworld.
- Is he defecting?
- We're not sure, sir.
He has taken refuge
in the ketha province,
a region uninhabited for decades.
He's gotta be hiding there, sir!
He knows if we even
go near klingon space,
it'd be all-out war.
Starfleet can't go after him, but I can.
Please, sir.
All-out war with
the klingons is inevitable, Mr. Kirk.
If you ask me, it's already begun.
Since we first learned of their existence,
the klingon empire
has conquered and occupied
two planets that we know of
and fired on our ships
half a dozen times.
They are coming our way.
London was not an archive.
It was a top-secret branch of starfleet
designated section 31.
They were developing
defense technology
and training our officers
to gather intelligence
on the klingons
and any other potential enemy
who means to do us harm.
Harrison was one of our top agents.
Well, now he's a fugitive
and I want to take him out.
Pike always said you were
one of our best and brightest.
You should have heard him defend you.
He's the one who talked you
into joining starfleet, wasn't he?
Yes, sir.
Did he ever tell you
who talked him into joining?
(Clicks tongue)
His death is on me.
And yours can't be.
Sir, please. All I...
Mr. Spock, you said the province
where Harrison is hiding is uninhabited?
Affirmative, sir.
As part of our defensive strategy,
31 developed a new photon torpedo.
(Beeping)
Long-range and untraceable,
it would be invisible to klingon sensors.
I don't want you hurt,
but I want to take him out.
You park on the edge
of the neutral zone,
you lock onto Harrison's position,
you fire, you kill him and you haul ass.
Permission to reinstate
Mr. Spock as my first officer.
Granted.
(Overlapping conversations)
Bones: Jim!
- Where were you?
- For what?
Your medical exam.
Ten hours ago, you were
in a damn firefight.
- Now it's my duty as ship's...
- I'm fine, bones.
The hell you are.
I'm fine.
Kirk: Status report,
Mr. Spock. (Grunts)
The enterprise should be
ready for launch
by the time we arrive.
- Good. Good.
- Captain.
Thank you for requesting
my reinstatement.
You're welcome.
As I am again
your first officer, it is now my duty
to strongly object
to our mission parameters.
Of course it is.
There is no starfleet regulation
that condemns a man
to die without a trial,
something you
and admiral Marcus are forgetting.
Also, preemptively firing torpedoes
at the klingon homeworld
goes against...
You yourself said
the area's uninhabited.
There's only gonna be one casualty.
And in case you weren't listening,
our orders have nothing to do
with starfleet regulation.
Wait a minute. We're firing
torpedoes at the klingons?
Regulations aside,
this action is morally wrong.
Regulations aside, pulling your ass
out of a volcano was morally right.
And I didn't win any points for that.
Whoa, Jim, calm down.
I'm not gonna take
ethics lessons from a robot!
Reverting to name-calling
suggests that you are defensive
and therefore find my opinion valid.
I wasn't asking for your opinion.
Bones, get that thing off my face.
Spock: Captain, our mission
could start a war with the klingons
and it is, by its very definition, immoral.
Perhaps you should
take the requisite time
to arrive at this conclusion for yourself.
Woman: Captain kirk.
Science officer Wallace.
I've been assigned
to the enterprise by admiral Marcus.
These are my transfer orders.
You requested an additional
science officer, captain?
I wish I had.
"Lieutenant Carol Wallace."
"Doctorate in applied physics
"specializing in advanced weaponry."
Spock: Impressive credentials.
Thank you.
But redundant now that
I am back aboard the enterprise.
And yet, the more the merrier.
- Have a seat, doctor.
- Thank you.
Shuttle crew, stand by for lift-off.
Scotty: No! I'm not signing anything!
Now, get these bloody things
off my ship! Captain!
Kirk: Is there a problem, Mr. Scott?
Aye, sir. I was just
explaining to this gentleman
that I cannae authorize any
weapons on board this ship
without knowing what's inside them.
Mr. Scott raises yet another point...
Report to the bridge.
Captain.
Mr. Scott, I understand your concerns,
but we need these torpedoes on board.
Due respect, sir,
but photon torpedoes run on fuel.
Now, I cannae detect the type of fuel
that's in the compartments
on these torpedoes
because it's shielded.
Now, I asked for
the specifications, but he said...
- It's classified.
So I said, "no specs, no signature!"
Sulu: Captain.
Flight check's complete.
We're good to go, sir.
- Thank you, Mr. Sulu.
- Yes, sir.
Now if you'll excuse me, sir,
I have a warp core to prime.
Get down!
Jim, your vitals are way off.
Report to the med bay. Scotty!
I need you to approve those weapons.
Do you know what this is, captain?
I don't have time for a lecture, Scotty.
- Do you know what this is?
- It's a warp core.
It's a radioactive
catastrophe waiting to happen.
A subtle shift in magnetic output
from, say, firing
one or more of six dozen torpedoes
with an unknown payload
could set off a chain reaction
which would kill
every living thing on this ship.
Letting those torpedoes on board the
enterprise is the last straw!
- What was the first straw?
- What was the...
There are plenty of straws.
How about starfleet
confiscating my transwarp equation?
And now some madman's
using it to hop across the galaxy!
Where do you think he got it from?
We have our orders, Scotty!
That's what scares me.
This is clearly a military operation.
Is that what we are now?
'Cause I thought we were explorers.
Sign for the torpedoes, that's an order.
Right, well, you leave me no choice
but to resign my duties.
Come on, Scotty.
You're giving me no choice, sir.
I will not stand by...
You're not giving me much of a choice.
Will you just
make an exception and sign...
Do you accept my resignation or not?
I do.
You are relieved, Mr. Scott.
Jim, for the love of god,
do not use those torpedoes.
Automated female voice:
Attention.
Warp core anti-matter
containment check
in three minutes.
U h u ra: Captain! I'm so sorry
about admiral pike.
We all are.
- Are you okay?
- Fine, thank you, lieutenant.
(Sighs)
Actually, Scotty just quit.
And your boyfriend's second-guessing
me every chance he gets.
I'm sorry, that was inappropriate.
It's just sometimes
I want to rip the bangs off his head.
- You know, maybe it's me. I...
- It's not you.
It's not?
Wait, are you guys...
Are you guys fighting?
I'd rather not talk about it, sir.
Oh, my god! What is that even like?
Your ears burning?
Chekov: Captain on the bridge!
Sulu: Captain.
Mr. Chekov. You've been
shadowing Mr. Scott.
You are familiar with
the engineering systems of this ship?
Affirmative, sir.
Good.
You're my new chief.
Go put on a red shirt.
Aye, captain.
Retract all moorings, Mr. Sulu.
Yes, sir.
(Mechanical whirring)
Automated female voice: Docking
clamps one, two, and three are released.
Automated male voice:
All moorings retracted.
Lieutenant uhura,
open a shipwide channel.
Uhura: Yes, sir.
Kirk: Mr. Chekov,
how we looking down there?
- All systems nominal, captain.
- Copy that.
Warp available at your command.
Thank you, Mr. Chekov.
- All right. Let's ride.
- Yes, sir.
(Panels beeping)
- (Radio frequencies open)
- Channel open, sir.
Kirk: Attention, crew of the enterprise.
As most of you know, Christopher pike,
former captain of this ship
and our friend,
is dead.
The man who killed him
has fled our system
and is hiding on the klingon homeworld,
somewhere he believes
we are unwilling to go.
We are on our way there now.
Per admiral Marcus, it is essential
that our presence go undetected.
Tensions between the federation
and the klingon empire have been high.
Any provocation could lead
to an all-out war.
I will personally lead a landing party
to an abandoned city
on the surface of kronos
where we will capture
the fugitive, John Harrison,
and return him to earth
so he can face judgment for his actions.
All right. Let's go
get this son of a bitch. Kirk out.
Captain, I believe you have
made the right decision.
If I can be of assistance,
I would be happy to accompany
you on the away team.
You? Happy?
I was simply attempting to use your
vernacular to convey an idea.
Thank you, Mr. Spock.
Man: (On pa) All personnel, prepare
for the closing of payload bay doors.
(Tricorder beeping)
Mr. Spock. You startled me.
What are you doing, doctor?
- Verifying that the torpedo's internal...
- You misunderstand.
What are you doing aboard this ship?
There is no record
of you being assigned to the enterprise.
Really? That must be
some sort of mistake.
My conclusion as well, Dr. Marcus.
Except that you have lied
about your identity.
Wallace is the surname of your mother.
I can only assume
the admiral is your father.
Mr. Spock.
I'm aware that I have
no right to ask this of you.
But please, he cannot
know that I'm here...
(All grunting)
Engineering manually
dropped us out of warp, sir.
Mr. Chekov, did you break my ship?
Sorry, sir. I don't know what happened!
The core overheated.
I had to activate the emergency stop.
It must be a coolant leak.
I need time to find it.
- Sorry, captain.
- Damn it.
(Sighs) Mr. Sulu,
time to our destination.
Twenty minutes, sir.
That's 20 minutes
in enemy space we weren't counting on.
All right. We better hop to it.
- Where's Spock?
- Here, captain.
You're coming with me to kronos.
Lieutenant, how's your klingon?
- It's rusty, but it's good.
- Good, you're coming, too.
This isn't going to be a problem, is it,
you two working together?
Absolutely not.
Unclear.
I'll meet you in the shuttle bay.
Jim, you're not actually
going down there, are you?
You don't Rob a bank
when the getaway car has a flat tire.
(Radio frequencies open)
I'm sure engineering
will have us all patched up
by the time we get back.
Isn't that right, Mr. Chekov?
Yes, captain.
- /'il do my best, sir.
- (Radio frequencies close)
Mr. Sulu, you have the conn.
Once we're en route,
I want you to transmit
a targeted comm burst
to Harrison's location.
You tell him you have a bunch
of real big torpedoes pointed at his head
and if he doesn't play nice,
you're not afraid to use them.
- Is that a problem?
- No, sir.
I've just never sat in the chair before.
You're gonna do great.
(Softly) Jim! Wait!
You just sat that man down
at a high-stakes poker game
with no cards and told him to bluff.
Now sulu's a good man,
but he is no captain.
For the next two hours, he is.
And enough with the metaphors,
all right? That's an order.
Kirk: Mr. Sulu, make sure
that k'normian ship is ready to fly.
(Radio frequencies open)
Acting captain 8qu to shuttle bay 2.
Please have the trade ship
we confiscated
during the mudd incident last month
fueled and flight ready.
Captain kirk is en route to you now.
Ready to deploy, captain.
Kirk: Lieutenants, lose the red shirts.
You are k'normian arms dealers.
Put those on.
- Sir?
- Look, if this thing goes south,
there can be nothing
tying us to starfleet.
Unless of course you want to
start a war, Mr. Hendorff.
- No, sir.
Good. Me, neither.
I am detecting
a single life sign in the ketha province.
Given the information
provided by Mr. Scott,
this is most likely John Harrison.
Mr. Sulu, I think we found our man.
You let him know you mean business.
Sulu: Aye, captain.
(Hailing frequencies opens)
Attention, John Harrison.
This is captain hikaru 8qu
of the u. S. 8. Enterprise.
A shuttle of highly trained officers
is on its way to your location.
If you do not surrender
to them immediately,
I will unleash the entire payload
of advanced long-range torpedoes
currently locked onto your location.
You have two minutes
to confirm your compliance.
Refusal to do so will result
in your obliteration.
If you test me, you will fail.
(Frequencies close)
Mr. Sulu,
remind me never to piss you off.
Spock: We will arrive
at Harrison's location
in three minutes, captain.
It is unlikely that he will come willingly.
I calculate the odds
of him attempting to kill us at 91 .6%.
Fantastic.
Good thing you don't care about dying.
I am sorry, lieutenant.
I could not hear what you said.
I didn't say anything.
Actually, I'd be happy to speak
- if you're willing to listen to me.
- Guys...
Lieutenant, I would prefer
to discuss this in private.
You'd prefer not to discuss this at all.
Spock: Our current circumstances...
Are you really gonna do this right now?
What never seems to require
your undivided focus...
I'm sorry, captain, just two seconds.
- Okay.
- Is us.
At that volcano, you didn't
give a thought to us.
What it would do to me
if you died, Spock.
You didn't feel anything.
You didn't care.
And I'm not the only one who's upset
with you. The captain is, too.
Wha... no, no, no.
Don't drag me into this.
She is right.
Your suggestion that
I do not care about dying is incorrect.
A sentient being's optimal chance
at maximizing their utility
is a long and prosperous life.
Great.
Not exactly a love song, Spock.
You misunderstand.
It is true I chose not to feel anything
upon realizing that
my own life was ending.
As admiral pike was dying,
I joined with his consciousness
and experienced what he felt
at the moment of his passing.
Anger. Confusion.
Loneliness.
Fear
I had experienced those feelings before,
multiplied exponentially
on the day my planet was destroyed.
Such a feeling is something I choose
never to experience again.
Nyota, you mistake my choice not to feel
as a reflection of my not caring.
Well, I assure you,
the truth is precisely the opposite.
- (Disruptors firing)
- (Alarms blaring)
What the hell was that?
What happened? Where's their signal?
It cut out. I'm working to get them back.
We are being pursued by
a d-4 class klingon vessel.
I thought this sector was abandoned!
It must be a random patrol.
Hold on!
This ship has no offensive capabilities.
It's got us. Give me all six fuel cells.
- Spock: Aye, captain.
- (Grunts)
(Alarm blaring)
Damn it!
They're closing fast, bearing 285!
All right, there! There!
We can lose them there.
If you are suggesting
that we utilize the passage
between the approaching structures,
- this ship will not fit.
- We'll fit.
- Captain, we will not fit.
- We'll fit, we'll fit!
(Strains)
(Screams)
(Grunts)
(All breathing heavily)
- I told you we'd fit.
- I am not sure that qualifies.
Any sign of them?
- No. Which worries me.
- Kirk: We lost them!
Or they're jamming our scanners.
Or we lost them.
(Klingon speaking over speakers)
Uhura: They're ordering us to land.
(Klingon continues)
Captain, they're gonna
want to know why we're here.
And they're gonna torture us.
Question us.
And they're gonna kill us.
So we come out shooting.
We're outnumbered, outgunned.
There's no way we survive
if we attack first.
You brought me here
because I speak klingon.
Then let me speak klingon.
Kirk: This isn't going to work.
Spock: It is our only logical option.
And if you interrupt her now, you will
not only incur the wrath of the klingons
but that of lieutenant uhura as well.
(Speaking klingon)
(Breathing heavily)
- Lieutenant.
- Thanks, captain.
(Speaking klingon)
(Whimpers)
(Screams)
(Klingons shouting)
- (Yells)
- (Grunts)
(Weapons fire continues)
- Spock: Stand down.
- How many torpedoes?
- Stand down!
- (Fires)
Harrison: The torpedoes,
the weapons you threatened
me with in your message.
How many are there?
Seventy-two.
I surrender.
(Groaning)
On behalf of Christopher pike,
my friend,
I accept your surrender.
(Grunting)
(Panting)
(Grunts)
Captain!
(Panting)
Captain.
(Thunder rumbles)
Cuff him.
(Communicator chirps)
- Bones, meet me in the brig.
- Bones: Be right there.
Lieutenant.
Contact starfleet, let them know
we have Harrison in custody,
and we'll be on our way once
the warp core is repaired.
Yes, sir.
Bones: Why the hell did he surrender?
Kirk: I don't know.
But he just took out a squad
of klingons single-handedly.
I want to know how.
Sounds like we have
a Superman on board.
Kirk: You tell me.
Put your arm through the hole.
I'm gonna take a blood sample.
(Injection whirs)
Why aren't we moving, captain?
An unexpected malfunction,
perhaps in your warp core
conveniently stranding you
on the edge of klingon space?
- How the hell do you know that?
- Bones.
I think you'd find
my insight valuable, captain.
- We good?
- Yeah.
Let me know what you find.
Ignore me and you
will get everyone on this ship killed.
Spock: Captain, I believe
he will only attempt to manipulate you.
I would not recommend
engaging the prisoner further.
Give me a minute.
Let me explain what's happening here.
You are a criminal.
I watched you murder
innocent men and women.
I was authorized to end you!
And the only reason
why you are still alive
is because I am allowing it.
So shut your mouth.
Oh, captain, are you going
to punch me again
over and over till your arm weakens?
Clearly you want to, so tell me,
why did you allow me to live?
We all make mistakes.
No. I surrendered to you because,
despite your attempt
to convince me othennise,
you seem to have
a conscience, Mr. Kirk.
If you did not,
then it would be impossible for me
to convince you of the truth.
23-17-46-11.
Coordinates not far from earth.
If you want to know why I did what I did,
go and take a look.
Give me one reason
why I should listen to you.
I can give you 72.
And they're on board your ship, captain.
They have been all along.
I suggest you open one up.
(Dance music playing)
(Music playing louder)
_ohl -hi!
You know what really
bothers me, though? (Burps)
It's the modifications,
you know, the enhancements.
Right? And then like that,
I'm off the ship!
Just for trying to do what's right!
And what did you do anyway?
You just stood there like an oyster,
- looking at me!
- (Communicator beeps)
- (Chirps)
- What?
Scotty, it's kirk.
Oh, well now!
If it isn't captain James
tiberius perfect hair!
Did you hear that?
I called him perfect hair. (Laughs)
- Where are you?
Are you drunk?
What I do in my private time
is my business, jimbo.
I need you to help me out
with something.
Will you take these coordinates down?
23-17-46-11.
Are you writing?
What, you don't think
I can remember four numbers?
(Snickers) Ye of little faith.
What was the third one?
Forty-six.
I don't know exactly
what you're looking for,
but I have a feeling you'll know it
when you see it.
You may have been right
about those torpedoes.
I will consider that an apology.
And I will consider that apology.
You are the one who quit.
You made me quit!
Mr. Scott? (Groans)
Scott.
The nerve of that guy!
I am not doing that man any favors!
All right, then!
Are you out of your corn-fed mind?
You're not actually going
to listen to this guy?
He killed pike, he almost killed you,
and now you think
it's a good idea to pop open a torpedo
because he dared you to.
Why did he save our lives, bones?
The doctor does have a point, captain.
Don't agree with me, Spock.
It makes me very uncomfortable.
Perhaps you, too, should learn
to govern your emotions, doctor.
In this situation, logic dictates...
Logic? Oh, my god! There's a maniac
trying to make us blow up
our own damn ship and...
That's not it.
I don't know why he surrendered,
but that's not it.
Look, we're gonna open a torpedo.
The question is how.
Bones: But, Jim,
without Mr. Scott on board,
who exactly is qualified
to just pop open
a four-ton stick of dynamite?
The admiral's daughter
appeared to have interest
in the torpedoes
and she is a weapons specialist.
Perhaps she could be of some use.
What admiral's daughter?
Carol Marcus. Your new science officer
concealed her identity to board the ship.
When were you going to tell me that?
When it became relevant. As it just did.
Are the torpedoes in the weapons bay?
Loaded and ready to fire.
What are they?
I don't know.
That's why I forged my transfer
onto your ship to find out why.
I do apologize for that.
By the way, if I caused you
any problems, I am sorry.
I'm Carol Marcus.
- James kirk.
- Torpedoes.
My father gave me access
to every program he oversaw,
then I heard he was
developing these prototype torpedoes.
When I went to confront him about it,
he wouldn't even see me.
That's when I discovered
the torpedoes had disappeared
from all official records.
And then he gave them to me.
You're much cleverer than
your reputation suggests, captain kirk.
I have a reputation?
Yes, you do. I'm a friend
of Christine chapel's.
(Instruments humming)
Christine, yes. How is she?
She transferred to the
outer frontier to be a nurse.
She's much happier now.
That's good.
You have no idea
who I'm talking about, do you?
What are we doing in here?
Is this shuttle prepped to fly?
Of course it is.
- Would you please turn around?
- Why?
Just turn around.
It's too dangerous to try and open
one of these torpedoes
on the enterprise.
But there is a nearby planetoid.
I can open one up there.
But I will need some help.
Turn around.
Now!
Sulu: Captain on the bridge!
Kirk: Mr. Sulu,
have doctors Marcus and McCoy
landed on the planetoid yet?
Sulu: Yes, sir. They're moving the
torpedo into position now.
Kirk: Good. Any activity
from the klingons?
Sulu: Not yet.
But if we're stuck
here much longer, they will find us.
Lieutenant uhura,
did you let starfleet know
we have Harrison in custody?
Yes, sir. No response yet.
Chekov: Engineering to bridge.
Hello. Captain, can you hear me?
Mr. Chekov, give me some good news.
We found the leak, sir,
but the damage is substantial.
We're working on it.
Kirk: Any idea what caused it?
No, sir. But I accept full responsibility.
Something tells me
it wasn't your fault. Stay on it.
Sulu: Shuttle is standing by, captain.
Bones, thanks for helping out.
Dr. Marcus asked
for the steadiest hands on the ship.
You know, when I dreamt
about being stuck
on a deserted planet
with a gorgeous woman,
there was no torpedo!
Kirk: Dr. McCoy, may/remind you,
you are not there to flirt.
So how can these legendary
hands help you, Dr. Marcus?
Bones!
Carol: To understand how
powerful these weapons are,
we need to open the warhead.
To do that, we need to
access the fuel compartment.
Unfortunately for us,
the warheads on these
weapons are live.
Sweetheart, I once performed
an emergency c-section
on a pregnant gorn.
Octuplets.
And let me tell you,
those little bastards bite.
(Groans) I think I can work
some magic on your missile.
Carol: Dr. McCoy,
there's a bundle of fiber optic cables
against the inner casing.
You'll need to cut the 23rd wire down.
Whatever you do,
do not touch anything else.
Do you understand?
Right. The thought
never crossed my mind.
Carol: Dr. McCoy,
wait for my word.
I'm rerouting the detonation processor.
- Are you ready?
- And raring.
- Good luck.
- (Yells)
Sir, the torpedo just armed itself.
Darwin: The warhead's gonna
detonate in 30 seconds, sir!
What the hell happened?
I can't get my arm out!
Target their signal.
Beam them back right now.
The transporter cannot differentiate
between Dr. McCoy and the torpedo.
We cannot beam back one
without the other.
Dr. Marcus, can you disarm it?
I'm trying. I'm trying.
Jim, get her the hell out of here!
No! If you beam me back, he dies!
Just let me do it!
Ten. Nine.
Eight.
Standing by to transport
Dr. Marcus on your command, sir.
(Groaning) Four. Three.
Shit!
- (Torpedo powers down)
- (Bones groaning)
- (Sighs)
- Spock: Deactivation successful,
captain.
(Radio frequencies open)
Dr. McCoy, are you all right?
Bones!
Jim?
You're going to want to see this.
(Instruments beeping)
Man 1: (On radio) Delta team, deliver
your thrusters to loading clock 12.
Man 2: U.S.S. Vengeance, bridge crew
requesting entry to construction hangar.
Man 1: You are cleared
to enter the hangar.
Man 3: I need a welding team
on the number one nacelle.
Holy...
What have we got?
Carol: It's quite clever actually.
This fuel container's been
removed from the torpedo
and retrofitted to hide this cryo tube.
- Is he alive?
- Bones: He's alive.
But if we try to revive him
without the proper sequencing,
it could kill him.
This technology's beyond me.
How advanced, doctor?
It's not advanced.
That cryo tube is ancient.
We haven't needed to freeze anyone
since we developed warp capability,
which explains the most interesting
thing about our friend here.
He's 300 years old.
Why is there a man in that torpedo?
There are men and women
in all those torpedoes, captain.
I put them there.
Who the hell are you?
A remnant of a time long past.
Genetically engineered to be superior
so as to lead others
to peace in a world at war.
But we were condemned as
criminals, forced into exile.
For centuries we slept,
hoping when we awoke,
things would be different.
But as a result
of the destruction of vulcan,
your starfleet began
to aggressively search
distant quadrants of space.
My ship was found adrift.
I alone was revived.
Kirk: I looked up "John Harrison."
Until a year ago, he didn't exist.
John Harrison was a fiction
created the moment I was awoken
by your admiral Marcus
to help him advance his cause.
A smokescreen
to conceal my true identity.
My name is
Khan.
Why would a starfleet admiral
ask a 300-year-old frozen man for help?
Because I am better.
- At what?
- Everything.
Alexander Marcus needed to respond to
an uncivilized threat in a civilized time
and for that he needed a warrior's mind.
My mind.
To design weapons and warships.
Spock: You are suggesting the admiral
violated every regulation
he vowed to uphold
simply because he wanted
to exploit your intellect.
He wanted to exploit my savagery.
Intellect alone is useless
in a fight, Mr. Spock.
You... you can't even break a rule.
How would you be
expected to break bone?
Marcus used me to design weapons.
To help him realize
his vision of a militarized starfleet.
He sent you to use those weapons.
To fire my torpedoes
on an unsuspecting planet.
And then he purposely
crippled your ship
in enemy space,
leading to one inevitable outcome.
The klingons would come searching
for whomever was responsible,
and you would have
no chance of escape.
Marcus would finally
have the war he talked about.
The war he always wanted.
No. No.
I watched you open fire
in a room full of
unarmed starfleet officers.
You killed them in cold blood!
Marcus took my crew from me.
You are a murderer!
He used my friends to control me.
I tried to smuggle them to safety
by concealing them in the very weapons
I had designed,
but I was discovered.
I had no choice but to escape alone.
And when I did,
I had every reason to suspect
that Marcus had killed every single one
of the people I hold most dear.
So I responded in kind.
My crew
is my family, kirk.
Is there anything
you would not do for your family?
- (Alarm beeps)
- Sulu: Proximity alert, sir!
There's a ship at warp
heading right for us.
- Klingons?
- Khan: At warp?
No, kirk.
- We both know who it is.
- Sulu: I don't think so.
It's not coming at us from kronos.
Lieutenant, move Khan to med bay.
Post six security officers on him.
Yes, captain.
- Sulu: Captain on the bridge!
- (Crew talking indistinctly)
Kirk: Eta of the incoming ship.
Three seconds, sir.
(Alarm blaring)
- Shields.
- Aye, captain.
(Talking continues)
They're hailing us, sir.
On screen.
Broadcast shipwide, for the record.
Captain kirk.
(Sighs)
Admiral Marcus. I wasn't expecting you.
That's a hell of a ship you got there.
And I wasn't expecting to get word
that you'd taken Harrison into custody
in violation of your orders.
Well, we...
We had to improvise
when our warp core
unexpectedly malfunctioned.
But you already knew that,
didn't you, sir?
Marcus: / don't take your meaning.
Well, that's why you're here, isn't it?
To assist with our repairs?
Why else would the head of starfleet
personally come to the edge
of the neutral zone?
Captain, they're scanning our ship.
Is there something
I can help you find, sir?
Where is your prisoner, kirk?
Kirk: Per starfleet regulation,
I'm planning on returning Khan
to earth to stand trial.
Well, shit.
You talked to him.
This is exactly what I was
hoping to spare you from.
I took a tactical risk
and I woke that bastard up,
believing that his superior intelligence
could help us protect ourselves
from whatever came at us next.
But I made a mistake.
And now the blood
of everybody he's killed is on my hands.
So I'm asking you,
give him to me
so that I can end what I started.
And what exactly
would you like me to do
with the rest of his crew, sir?
Fire them at the klingons?
End 72 lives?
Start a war in the process?
He put those people in those torpedoes.
And I simply didn't want to burden you
with knowing what was inside of them.
You saw what this man
can do all by himself.
Can you imagine what would happen
if we woke up the rest of his crew?
What else did he tell you?
That he's a peacekeeper?
He's playing you, son,
don't you see that?
Khan and his crew were condemned
to death as war criminals.
And now it is our duty
to carry out that sentence
before anybody else
dies because of him.
Now, I'm going to ask you again!
One last time, son.
Lower your shields.
Tell me where he is.
He's in engineering, sir.
(Sighs) But I'll have him moved
to the transporter room right away.
I'll take it from here.
Do not drop those shields,
- Mr. Sulu.
- Sulu: Aye, captain.
Captain, given your awareness
of Khan's true location in the med bay,
may I know the details of your plan?
I told Marcus we were
bringing a fugitive back to earth.
That's what we're going to do.
- (Radio frequencies open)
- Mr. Chekov, can we warp?
Sir, if we go to warp,
we run the risk of
seriously damaging the core!
- Kirk: Can we do it?
- (Sighs in frustration)
Technically, yes, but I
would not advise it, captain.
-Noted. _(Frequencies close)
Mr. Sulu, set course for earth.
Yes, sir.
Punch it.
Well, at least we're moving again.
(Beeping)
If you think you're safe
at warp, you're wrong.
Lieutenant uhura, contact starfleet.
Tell them we were pursued
into the neutral zone
by an unmarked federation ship.
Comms are down, sir.
Permission to come on the bridge.
Kirk: Dr. Marcus.
He's gonna catch up with us,
and when he does,
the only thing
that's gonna stop him destroying
this ship is me,
so you have to let me talk to him.
Carol, we're at warp.
He can't catch up with us.
Yes, he can.
He's been developing a ship
that has advanced warp capabilities...
Captain! I'm getting
a reading I don't understand.
(Crew grunting)
(People screaming)
- Where are we?
- We're 237,000 kilometers from earth.
- Kirk: Damage report!
- Weapons are way down.
- Sulu: Shields are dropping.
- We're defenseless, sir.
Sir, we have a bulkhead breach.
- Where's the damage?
- Major hull damage, captain.
(Firing continues)
(Screaming)
(Grunting)
Evasive maneuvers! Get us to earth!
Right now!
Captain! Stop!
Everybody on this ship is going to die
if you don't let me speak to him.
(Alarms blaring)
Uhura, hail him.
Sir. It's me. It's Carol.
(Firing stops)
What are you doing on that ship?
I heard what you said.
That you made a mistake
and now you're doing
everything you can to fix it.
But, dad,
(stammering) I don't believe that
the man who raised me
is capable of destroying a ship
full of innocent people.
And, if I'm wrong about that,
then you're gonna have to
do it with me on board.
Actually, Carol, I won't.
- Jim...
- Can we intercept the transport signal?
No, sir.
- (Screams)
- Carol!
Captain kirk, without authorization
and in league with
the fugitive John Harrison,
you went rogue in enemy territory,
leaving me no choice
but to hunt you down and destroy you.
- Lock phasers.
- Wait, sir, wait, wait, wait!
I'll make this quick.
Target all aft torpedoes
on the enterprise bridge.
Sir, my crew
was just following my orders.
I take full responsibility for my actions.
But they were mine
and they were mine alone.
If I transmit Khan's location to you now,
all that I ask is that you spare them.
Please, sir.
I'll do anything you want.
Just let them live.
That's a hell of an apology.
But if it's any consolation,
I was never going to spare your crew.
Fire when...
I'm sorry.
(Gasps)
(Powering down)
Our weapons won't fire, sir!
Our shields are down!
We're losing power!
Someone in engineering
just manually reset our systems!
What do you mean, "someone"?
(Shouts) Who?
Their weapons have powered down. Sir.
Scotty: (On radio)
Enterprise! Can you hear me?
Scotty!
Guess what I found behind Jupiter.
- You're on that ship!
- / snuck on.
And seeing as I've just
committed an act of treason
against a starfleet
admiral, I'd really like
to get off this bloody ship.
Now beam me out!
You're a miracle worker.
We're a little low on power right now.
Just stand by. Stand by.
What do you mean, "low on power"?
What happened to the enterprise?
- (Doors opening)
- Call you back.
Scotty!
Spock. Our ship, how is she?
Our options are limited, captain.
We cannot fire and we cannot flee.
There is one option.
Uhura, when you get Scotty back,
- patch him through.
- Yes, sir.
Mr. Spock, you have the conn.
Captain, I strongly object.
To what? I haven't said anything yet.
Since we cannot take
the ship from the outside,
the only way we can take it
is from within.
And as a large boarding party
would be detected,
it is optimal for you to take
as few members
of the crew as possible.
You will meet resistance,
requiring personnel
with advanced combat abilities
and innate knowledge of that ship.
This indicates that
you plan to align with Khan,
the very man
we were sent here to destroy.
Kirk: I'm not aligning with him,
I'm using him.
"The enemy of my enemy is my friend."
An arabic proverb attributed
to a prince who was
betrayed and decapitated
by his own subjects.
Still, it's a hell of a quote.
- I will go with you, captain.
- No, I need you on the bridge.
I cannot allow you to do this.
It is my function aboard
this ship to advise you
on making the wisest
decisions possible,
something I firmly believe
you are incapable
of doing in this moment.
You're right!
What I'm about to do,
it doesn't make any sense,
it's not logical. It is a gut feeling.
I have no idea what I'm supposed to do.
I only know what I can do.
The enterprise and her crew
need someone
in that chair that knows what he's doing.
And it's not me.
It's you, Spock.
(Medical crew
speaking indistinctly)
Tell me everything you know
about that ship.
Dreadnought class.
Two times the size,
three times the speed.
Advanced weaponry.
Modified for a minimal crew.
Unlike most federation vessels,
it's built solely for combat.
I will do everything I can
to make you answer for what you did.
But right now I need your help.
In exchange for what?
You said you'd do anything
for your crew.
- I can guarantee their safety.
- Captain.
You can't even guarantee
the safety of your own crew.
Bones, what are you doing
with that tribble?
The tribble's dead.
I'm injecting Khan's platelets into
the deceased tissue of a necrotic host.
(Injection whirs)
Khan's cells regenerate
like nothing I've ever seen,
and I want to know why.
You coming with me or not?
You want to do what?
We're coming over there.
Sulu's maneuvering
the enterprise
into position as we speak.
To this ship? How?
There's a cargo door,
hangar 7, access port 101a.
You need to find
the manual override to open that airlock.
Are you crazy? Whoever you are.
Just listen to him, Scotty.
It's gonna be all right.
It is not gonna be all right.
You want me to open
an airlock into space,
whereupon I will freeze,
die and explode!
Lieutenant,
from our current position, is it possible
to establish contact with new vulcan?
- I'll do my best.
- Thank you.
Mr. Sulu, what is
the status of the other ship?
Their systems are still offline.
I'm aligning our ship now.
Scotty, how we doing over there?
Scotty: Captain,
I wish I had better news.
They've locked out access
to the ship's computer.
They'll have full weapons in
three minutes.
That means next time
I won't be able to stop them
destroying the enterprise. Stand by.
Commander, our trash exhaust
is aimed at
access port 101a of the other ship.
Captain, the ships are aligned.
Copy that.
- Scotty!
- I'm in the hangar. Give me a minute.
(Panting)
I'm running. Stand by.
(Panting and groaning)
Whoa, whoa, hold on, now, captain.
This door is very wee.
I mean, you know, small.
It's four square meters, tops.
It's gonna be like
jumping out of a moving car,
off a bridge, into your shot glass.
It's okay. I've done it before.
Yeah, it was vertical.
We jumped onto a... it was a...
(Muttering)
It doesn't matter. Scotty...
Did you find the manual override?
The manual override, Scotty.
Not yet, not yet.
(Panel beeping)
Captain, before you launch,
you should be aware there is
a considerable debris field
between our ships.
- Spock, not now. Scotty, you good?
- It's not easy!
Just give me two seconds,
all right, you mad bastard!
Tell me this is gonna work.
I have neither the information
nor the confidence to do so, doctor.
Scotty: Okay, captain, stand by.
Boy, you're a real comfort.
- Come on, come on, come on.
- (Beeping)
Yes!
Okay, okay! I'm set to open the door.
You ready?
Are you?
Kirk: Spock, pull the trigger.
Yes, captain.
Launching activation sequence on
three,
two,
one.
Sir, kirk is headed for collision at .432!
Captain, there is debris directly ahead.
Copy that.
Whoa! Jim, you're way off course!
I know, I know! I can see that.
- (Phaser humming)
- Guard: Don't move.
Use your display compass, captain.
You must correct precisely
- 37.243 degrees.
- Kirk: Got it.
I'm working my way back.
Scotty, you're gonna be ready
with that door, right?
What are you doing in here?
Wee bit of maintenance
on the airlock console. You're big.
Mr. Scott, where are you?
Captain, he can't seem to hear you.
I'm working on getting
his signal back. Stand by.
(Glass cracks)
- Damn it.
- Spock: Captain, what is it?
My helmet was hit.
Uhura, tell me you have Mr. Scott back.
Not yet. I'm still working on a signal.
His communicator is working.
- I don't know why he isn't responding.
- What is that?
Are you starfleet or private security?
Show me your other hand.
Because you look like private security.
Ensign: Imminent collision detected!
Khan, use evasive action!
- There is debris directly ahead.
- I see it.
- (Beeping)
- Mr. Sulu, did we lose Khan?
I don't know, commander.
I'm having trouble
tracking him in all this debris.
Was Khan hit?
We are trying to find him now.
Captain, you need to adjust
your target destination
to 183 by 473 degrees.
(Glass cracking)
Spock, my display's dead.
I'm flying blind.
Captain, without your display compass,
hitting your target destination
is mathematically impossible.
Spock, if I get back,
we really need to talk
about your bedside manner.
Commander, he's not going to make it.
(Beeps)
My display is still functioning.
I see you, kirk,
you're 200 meters ahead of me
at my one o'clock.
Come to your left
a few degrees and follow me.
Scotty, we're getting close.
We need a warm welcome.
Do you copy? Do you copy? Scotty?
If you can hear us, Mr. Scott,
- open the door in ten, nine...
- Scotty!
That person counting down,
- what is that?
- Eight...
Scotty: I think
you're hearing things, mate.
- A_seven_.
- Mr. Scott, where are you?
- Spock: Six, five...
- 1,800 meters. 1,600 meters.
- Scotty, where are you?
- Three...
- Do you copy, Scotty? Please!
- Two...
- Sorry about this.
- About what?
- Mr. Scott, open the door!
- Open the door!
- Spock: Mr. Scott, now!
- (Gasps)
(Guard screaming)
- (Yelling)
- (Grunts)
(Gasps)
(Grunting)
(Panting)
Welcome aboard.
- It's good to see you, Scotty.
- Who is that?
(Groaning)
Khan, Scotty. Scotty, Khan.
Hello.
They'll know we're here.
I know the best way to the bridge.
It's locked to stun.
Theirs won't be.
Try not to get shot.
(Phasers humming)
Commander, I have that
transmission as requested.
On screen, please.
Uhura: Stand by.
Mr. Spock.
Guard: Admiral.
I'll deal with you in a...
I am ashamed to be your daughter.
(Door opens)
Sir, we just had
a hangar door open on deck 13.
Khan.
Scotty: They're going to have
full power and we're walking?
The turbolifts are easily tracked
and Marcus would have us in a cage.
This path runs adjacent
to the engine room.
They know they
won't be able to use their weapons here
without destabilizing the warp core,
which gives us the advantage.
- Where'd you find this guy?
- It's a long story.
Spock: / will be brief.
In your travels, did you ever
encounter a man named Khan?
As you know,
I have made a vow
never to give you information
that could potentially alter your destiny.
Your path is yours to walk,
and yours alone.
That being said,
Khan noonien Singh is
the most dangerous adversary
the enterprise ever faced.
He is brilliant, ruthless,
and he will not hesitate to kill
every single one of you.
Did you defeat him?
At great cost. Yes.
How?
I don't mean to tempt fate here,
but where is everybody?
The ship is designed
to be flown by minimal crew,
one, if necessary.
- One? I...
- (Grunting)
(Groaning)
(Groans)
- You all right?
- Yeah. Where's Khan?
Lieutenant, I need you to
assemble all senior medical
and engineering staff
in the weapons bay.
All right.
Dr. McCoy, you inadvertently
activated a torpedo.
Could you replicate the process?
Why the hell would I want to do that?
Can you or can you not?
Damn it, man, I'm a doctor,
not a torpedo technician!
The fact that you
are a doctor is precisely
why I need you to listen very carefully.
Where is he?
Shit!
Khan: This way.
The minute we get
to the bridge, drop him.
What, stun him? Khan?
I thought he was helping us.
I'm pretty sure we're helping him.
(Doors opening)
Power coming online, sir!
Retarget the enterprise now.
- Crewman: Aye, sir.
- (Phasers firing)
(Men grunting)
Make sure he stays down.
- Excuse me.
- Yeah.
Admiral Marcus, you're under arrest.
You're not actually
going to do this, are you?
Admiral, get out of the chair.
You better stop
and think about what you're doing, kirk.
You better think about
what you did on kronos.
You made an incursion
onto an enemy planet!
You killed a klingon patrol.
Even if you got away without
a trace, war is coming.
And who is going to lead us? You?
If I'm not in charge,
our entire way of life is decimated!
So you want me off this ship,
you better kill me.
I'm not going to kill you, sir.
But I could stun your ass
and drag you out of that chair.
I'd rather not do that
in front of your daughter.
- You all right?
- Yes, captain.
- (Grunts)
- Jim!
(Grunts)
- (Groans)
- (Yells)
Listen! Wait!
(Grunts)
- (Bone cracks)
- (Screams)
(Marcus groaning)
- You...
- (Screaming)
You should have let me sleep.
- (Marcus screaming)
- (Skull cracking)
(Screaming)
Where is the captain, Mr. Sulu?
Our sensor array's down, sir.
I can't find him.
(Kirk grunts)
I'm going to make this
very simple for you.
- Captain.
- Your crew for my crew.
You betrayed us.
You are smart, Mr. Spock.
Spock don't... (Groans)
Mr. Spock, give me my crew.
And what will you do
when you get them?
Continue the work we were doing
before we were banished.
Which, as I understand it,
involves the mass genocide
of any being you find to be
less than superior.
Shall I destroy you, Mr. Spock?
Or will you give me what I want?
We have no transporter capabilities.
Fortunately mine are
perfectly functional.
Drop your shields.
If I do so, I have no guarantee
that you will not destroy the enterprise.
Well, let's play this out
logically then, Mr. Spock.
Firstly, I will kill your captain
to demonstrate my resolve.
Then if yours holds,
I will have no choice
but to kill you and your entire crew.
If you destroy our ship,
you will also destroy your own people.
Your crew requires oxygen
to survive, mine does not.
I will target your life support systems
located behind the aft nacelle.
And after every single person
aboard your ship suffocates,
I will walk over your cold
corpses to recover my people.
Now,
shall we begin?
Lower shields.
- (Beeping)
- (Shields power down)
A wise choice, Mr. Spock.
(Grunts)
- (Gasps)
- (Coughing)
(Panel beeping)
Khan: I see your 72 torpedoes
are still in their tubes.
If they are not mine,
commander, I will know it.
Vulcans do not lie.
The torpedoes are yours.
(Beeping)
Thank you, Mr. Spock.
I have fulfilled your terms.
Now fulfill mine.
Khan: Well, kirk,
it seems apt to return you to your crew.
- (Groaning)
- After all,
no ship should go down
without her captain.
(Alarms blaring)
He's locking phasers on us, sir!
- Let us out of here now!
- (Explosion)
(All grunting)
- (Crew clamoring)
- Shields at 6%!
The torpedoes!
How much time, lieutenant?
Twelve seconds, sir!
Crew of the enterprise,
prepare for imminent
proximity detonation.
What's he talking about?
What detonation?
The torpedoes.
He armed the damn torpedoes!
(Powering up)
(Grunting)
Sir, their weapons
have been knocked out.
- Not bad, commander.
- Thank you, lieutenant.
- Bones!
- Bones: Nurse!
- I got you. I got you.
- Dr. Marcus.
- (Groaning)
Good to see you, Jim.
You helped Spock
detonate those torpedoes?
Damn right I did.
He killed Khan's crew!
Spock's cold, but he's not that cold.
I've got Khan's crew.
Seventy-two human popsicles
safe and sound in their cryo tubes.
- Son of a bitch!
- (Ship powering down)
Crewman: Sir, the central
power grid is failing!
- Switch to auxiliary power.
- Auxiliary power failing, sir.
Sulu: Commander, our ship's
caught in earth's gravity!
- Can we stop?
- I can't do anything.
(Screaming)
Sorry! Oh, no.
Clear the area!
Engage emergency lockdown!
I hope you don't get seasick.
- Do you?
- Yeah.
Lieutenant, sound evacuation, all decks.
Aye, sir.
As acting captain,
I order you to abandon this ship.
I will remain behind and divert all power
to life support
and evacuation shuttle bays.
Automated female voice:
Evacuation protocols...
I order you to abandon the ship!
All due respect, commander,
but we're not going anywhere.
Attention all decks.
Evacuation protocols initiated.
One day I've been off this ship!
One bloody day!
(Screaming)
Gravity systems are failing.
Hold on! Hold on!
(Grunting)
(Crew screaming)
Automated female voice:
Attention, all decks.
Evacuation protocols initiated.
- (Woman screaming)
- Proceed to exit bays
- and report to your assigned shuttle.
- (Panting)
Scotty: There won't be time
for evacuation
if we don't get power
to stabilize the damn ship!
- Can we restore it?
- Only from engineering.
We have to get back to the warp core.
- Attention all decks.
- (Crew screaming)
Jim?
Kirk: Scotty, we got to get
the power back on! Come on!
(Both panting)
- Scotty, we got to jump!
- What?
Jump! Jump!
- Oh, god.
- (Both grunting)
Emergency power at 15% and dropping.
Automated female voice:
Attention, all decks.
Evacuation protocols initiated.
Proceed to exit bays
and report to your assigned shuttle.
(Both yelling)
(Straining and grunting)
(Screaming)
- Jim?
- Hold on!
I can't.
(Straining)
(Grunting)
(Gasping)
- (Grunting)
- (Laughs)
I've got you, captain!
- Chekov.
- Don't let go!
(Straining)
Even if we get the warp core online,
we've still got to redirect the power!
- He's right, captain!
- What are you talking about?
Someone has to hit
the manual override.
Laddie, there's a switch...
Behind the deflector dish!
I'll flip the switch!
Let's go!
(Grunting)
Oh, no.
(Whimpering)
Oy-yoy! Oy-yoy! Oy-yoy-yoy!
(Screaming)
Evacuation protocols initiated.
Proceed to exit bays
and report to your assigned shuttle.
(All screaming)
Mr. Sulu, divert
any remaining power to stabilizers.
Doing what I can, sir. Doing what I can.
(Panting)
(Grunting)
(Beeping)
(Straining)
(Powering up)
Automated female voice:
Core misaligned. Danger.
- Oh, no, no, no, no!
- What?
The housings are misaligned!
There's no way
we can redirect the power!
The ship's dead, sir. She's gone.
- No, she's not.
- Wait, Jim!
If we go in there, we'll die!
Do you hear me?
The radiation will kill us!
Will you listen to me?
What the hell are you doing?
I'm opening the door. I'm going in.
That door is there to stop us
from getting irradiated!
We'd be dead
before we made the climb!
You're not making the climb.
(Grunts)
Automated female voice:
Danger. Core misaligned.
(Grunting)
(Electricity crackling)
If we don't get power
or shields back online,
we're gonna be incinerated on re-entry!
(Grunts)
(Yells)
(Screams)
Warp core is back online!
Spock: Maximum thrusters, Mr. Sulu!
Thrusters at maximum!
Stand by! Stand by!
(Engines engaging)
(Chuckles softly)
- Shields restored!
- Commander, power online.
Mr. Spock, altitude stabilizing.
It's a miracle.
There are no such things.
(Communicator beeping)
Scotty: Engineering to bridge.
- Mr. Spock!
- Mr. Scott.
Sir, you'd better get down here.
Better hurry.
Open it.
The decontamination process
is not complete.
You'd flood the whole compartment.
The door's locked, sir.
(Groaning)
(Groans)
(Breathing heavily)
(Mechanism whirring)
How's our ship?
Out of danger.
You saved the crew.
You used what he wanted against him.
That's a nice move.
It is what you would have done.
And this,
this is what you would have done.
It was only logical.
I'm scared, Spock.
Help me not be.
How do you choose not to feel?
I do not know.
Right now I am failing.
I want you to know
why I couldn't let you die.
Why I went back for you.
Because you are my friend.
(Coughs)
(Yelling) Khan!
God, that was close!
Set destination, starfleet headquarters!
Automated male voice:
Engines compromised.
Cannot guarantee destination.
Confirm order.
Confirm.
(Rumbling)
(Concerned murmuring)
(Crowd exclaiming in shock)
(Clamoring)
(All screaming)
Search the enemy ship for signs of life.
Sir, there's no way anyone survived.
He could.
Yes, sir.
(Sirens wailing)
(Grunts)
(Alarms blaring)
Whoa! Hejustjumped 30 meters!
Can we beam him up?
Chekov: There's too much damage.
I have no incoming signal.
But it may be possible
to beam you down, sir.
Go get him.
- Stand by for coordinates.
- Yes, sir.
Enter 3517 by 2598.
Coordinates confirmed.
(People clamoring)
(Sighs)
(Tribble chittering softly)
(Equipment beeping)
Get me a cryo tube, now!
(Grunting)
(Yelling in pain)
(Injection whirs)
Get this guy out of the cryo tube.
Keep him in an induced coma.
We're gonna put kirk inside.
It's our only chance to
preserve his brain function.
How much of Khan's blood is left?
None.
Enterprise to Spock. Spock!
(Grunts)
(Straining)
Activate the cryogenic sequence.
- (Beeping)
- (Hissing)
McCoy to bridge.
I can't reach Spock. I need Khan alive.
You get that son of a bitch
back on board right now!
I think he can save kirk.
Can we beam them up to the ship?
They keep moving! I can't
get a lock on either of them.
Can you beam someone down?
(Both straining)
(Yelling)
- (Screams)
- Spock!
Spock!
Spock, stop! Stop!
He's our only chance to save kirk!
George: What is it?
Winona: It's a boy.
George: Let's call him Jim.
Pike: Your father was
captain of a starship for 12 minutes.
He saved 800 lives.
I dare you to do better.
(Gasps)
Don't be so melodramatic.
You were barely dead.
It was the transfusion
that really took its toll.
You were out cold for two weeks.
Transfusion?
Your cells were heavily irradiated.
We had no choice.
Khan?
Once we caught him,
I synthesized a serum
from his superblood.
Tell me, are you feeling homicidal?
Power mad? Despotic?
No more than usual.
How'd you catch him?
I didn't.
You saved my life.
Uhura and I had
something to do with it, too, you know.
You saved my life, captain.
And the lives...
Spock, just...
Thank you.
You are welcome, Jim.
Kirk: There will always be
those who mean to do us harm.
To stop them,
we risk awakening
the same evil within ourselves.
Our first instinct is to seek revenge
when those we love are taken from us.
But that's not who we are.
We are here today
to rechristen the USS. Enterprise,
and to honor those who lost their lives
nearly one year ago.
When Christopher pike
first gave me his ship
he had me recite the captain's oath,
words I didn't appreciate at the time.
Now I see them as a call
for us to remember
who we once were,
and who we must be again.
And those words?
Space, the final frontier.
These are the voyages
of the starship enterprise.
Her five-year mission,
to explore strange new worlds,
to seek out new life
and new civilizations,
to boldly go
where no one has gone before.
Chekov: Captain on the bridge.
It's hard to get out of it
once you've had a taste,
isn't that right, Mr. Sulu?
"Captain" does have a nice ring to it.
Chair's all yours, sir.
Mr. Scott.
How's our core?
Purring like a kitten, captain.
She's ready for a long journey.
Excellent.
Come on, bones! It's gonna be fun.
Five years in space. God help me.
Dr. Marcus.
I'm glad you could be
a part of the family.
It's nice to have a family.
Kirk: Spock.
Captain.
Where shall we go?
As a mission of this duration
has never been attempted,
I defer to your good judgment, captain.
Mr. Sulu, take us out.
Aye, captain.